<chapter id="dice_c">
<title></title>
<sect1 id="dice">
<title>Data Ice Model</title>

<sect2 id="dice_modes">
<title>Modes</title>

<para> 
The default science mode of the data model is the COPYALL mode.
COPYALL mode will examine the fields found in all input data streams,
if any input field names match the field names used internally,
they are copied into the export array and passed directly to the coupler
without any special user code.
There are several other scientific modes supported by the model, they are listed below.
The mode is selected by a character string set in the strdata namelist variable dataMode.
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry><term><option>dataMode = "NULL" </option></term><listitem><para>
NULL mode turns off the data model as a provider of data to the coupler.
The ice_present flag will be set to false
and the coupler will assume no exchange of data to or from the data model.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>dataMode = "COPYALL" </option></term><listitem><para>
COPYALL mode copies all fields directly from the input data streams
Any required fields not found on an input stream will be set to zero.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>dataMode = "SSTDATA" </option></term><listitem><para>
SSTDATA is a prognostic mode.  It requires data be sent to the ice model.  
Ice fraction (extent) data is read from an input stream, atmosphere state
variables are received from the coupler, and then an atmosphere-ice surface flux 
is computed and sent to the coupler.  It is called "SSTDATA" mode because
normally the ice fraction data is found in the same data files that provide
SST data to the data ocean model.  They are normally found in the same file
because the SST and ice fraction data are derived from the same observational
data sets and are consistent with each other.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="dice_namelist">
<title>Namelist</title>

<para>

The data ice specific namelist input is as follows.  The namelist input
filename is hardwired in the data model code to "dice_in".  The namelist group is
called "dice_nml".  The variable formats are character string (char),
integer (int), double precision real (r8), or logical (log) or one dimensional arrays
of any of those things (array of ...).

</para>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry><term><option>ice_in (char) </option></term><listitem><para>
  sets the filename for the data ice strdata namelist.  this must be set.  default='unset'.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>decomp (char)</option></term><listitem><para>
  set the decomposition option for the data model.  valid options are placing the global array on the root task or a simple stride-one load balanced one-dimensional decomposition.  other decompositions may be added in the future.  valid values are ['root','1d'].  default='1d'.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>flux_swpf (r8)</option></term><listitem><para>
  this is the shortwave penetration factor as a fraction where 1.0 is 100% penetration.  used only in SSTDATA mode.  default=0.0
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>flux_Qmin (r8)</option></term><listitem><para>
  this is the minimum bound on the melt rate in kg/s/m2.  used only in SSTDATA mode.  default=-300.0
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>flux_Qacc (log)</option></term><listitem><para>
  this logical activates the water accumulation associated with the ocean potential to melt ice.  used only in SSTDATA mode.  default=false.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>flux_Qacc0 (r8)</option></term><listitem><para>
  this is the initial water accumulation value on a startup.  used only in SSTDATA mode.  default=0.0
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>restfilm (char)</option></term><listitem><para>
  restart filename for the data ice model data.  this is optional.  if this is unset, the restart filename will be read from the rpointer.ice file.  default='unset'.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry><term><option>restfils (char)</option></term><listitem><para>
  restart filename for the data ice stream data.  this is optional.  if this is unset, the restart filename will be read from the rpointer.ice file.  default='unset'.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>

The pre-defined internal field names in the data ice model are as follows.
In general, the stream input file should translate the input variable names into
these names for use within the data ice model.

</para>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="dice_fields">
<title>Fields</title>

<screen>
     (/"to              ","s               ","uo              ","vo              ", &
       "dhdx            ","dhdy            ","q               ","z               ", &
       "ua              ","va              ","ptem            ","tbot            ", &
       "shum            ","dens            ","swndr           ","swvdr           ", &
       "swndf           ","swvdf           ","lwdn            ","rain            ", &
       "snow            ","t               ","tref            ","qref            ", &
       "ifrac           ","avsdr           ","anidr           ","avsdf           ", &
       "anidf           ","tauxa           ","tauya           ","lat             ", &
       "sen             ","lwup            ","evap            ","swnet           ", &
       "swpen           ","melth           ","meltw           ","salt            ", &
       "tauxo           ","tauyo           " /)
</screen>

</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
